<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth and error discouered in two sermons in St Maries in Oxford. By Antony White Master of Arts of Corpus Christi Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>White, Anthony, 1588 or 9-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25376</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119899</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855105</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20577</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15075)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20577)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1016:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth and error discouered in two sermons in St Maries in Oxford. By Antony White Master of Arts of Corpus Christi Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>White, Anthony, 1588 or 9-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield printer to the famous Vniversity for Henry Curteyne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20577:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20577:1"/>
            <p>TRVTH AND ERROR DISCOVERED IN TWO SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS IN S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> ANTONY WHITE <hi>Maſter of Arts of Corpus Chriſti Colledge in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD</hi> Printed by IOHN LICHFIELD Printer to the Famous Vniverſity for <hi>Henry Curteyne.</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20577:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20577:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>HENRY NEVILL</hi> OF <hi>PILLINGBERE</hi> IN <hi>Berks</hi> his much honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Patron.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE life of man is a continuall war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, both againſt vices that aſſault the will, and errors which inuade the vnderſtanding. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst theſe eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the ſoule doe thoſe ſermons ſerue; eſpecially the latter,
<pb facs="tcp:20577:3"/>whoſe chiefe employment is, to weaken error by cutting of the auxiliary forces which bad af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections lend it, what ſeruice I haue herein done to the church and truth (which done by ſo raw a ſouldier in ſo ſhort a velitation can bee but ſmall) I bring vnder your view, and the like curteous eyes of thoſe to whom you ſhall pleaſe to ſhew it. <hi>I</hi> ſhould much feare the exactneſſe of your iudgement, did I not know it tempered with that candor which vſeth well to accept the honeſt endeavours of the weakeſt. In this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance I leaue you to the reading of theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſermons, reſting alwaies</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in my beſt ſervices ANTONY WHITE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20577:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROV. 23. VER. 23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Buy the truth but ſell it not.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T were as fruitleſſe a diligence for a Divine in writing of this na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, as this excellent book of Prouerbs is, to enquire out methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call connexions of ſentences, as it were for an artiſt to ſtudy the coherences of <hi>Bedes axiomes:</hi> Not therefore to trouble you with anxious prefaces this way let it ſuffice you (men, fathers, and brethren) that our royall Preacher doth in this verſe commend to his ſtudious hearers, a commodity fitteſt for hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature to deſire and enioy, <hi>Truth:</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which, his advice hath two branches, one in tearmes <hi>affirmatiue,</hi> it is to bee bought, the other in <hi>negatiue,</hi> it is not to be folde; of the firſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hopeing that the God of truth will aſſiſt me, and preſuming that your loue of truth will accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany me, I purpoſe for to ſpeake.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:20577:4"/>
            <p> Where firſt I muſt with <hi>Solomon</hi> take it for granted, that there is a <hi>truth,</hi> and that it may bee <hi>bought.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicero in Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cullo.</note> For I hope I am not come amongſt thoſe <hi>Academists</hi> of whoſe ſchoole, thoſe in <hi>Cicero,</hi> with <hi>Cicero</hi> himſelfe were, who with an incongruous confidence deliuer, that there is nothing of whoſe truth we may bee confidently aſſured.<note place="margin">Vide Lact. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> anſweres this folly wittily: <hi>Si nihil omnino ſcias, id ipſum nihil poſſeſciri, tolletur: if no truth may be knowen, why would they haue that paſſe for truth that nothing can be knowne</hi> Nay whereas it is their ambition to confute the opinions of all other men as falſe, how can this be without a ſecret profeſſion of ſome truth, for what can giue the foile to falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood but truth? Beſides whereas they allow ſome <hi>veriſimilitude,</hi> herein they confeſſe a <hi>truth,</hi> vnleſſe which <hi>Austen</hi> laughes at,<note place="margin">Aug lib. <hi>2.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Academicos</note> they will profeſſe that what they ſee is the likeneſſe and purtrature of that which they neuer ſaw.</p>
            <p>This ancient fancy hath not yet giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp the ghoſt euen in our daies; nor will, as long as there remaines in the world, ſo much ignorance, lazines; iealouſie, pride, prophanes for each of theſe lend ſomewhat to this opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: an <hi>ignorant</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lead by the examples of thoſe many things which he is not able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, concludes in haſt that nothing may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended; as if nothing were to be bought, becauſe through his blindneſſe hee ſees nothing in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket. The <hi>lazy</hi> one, quickly weary of the ſearch of truth, impatient of any longer labour, reſts conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the firſt appearances of things, and giues
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20577:4"/>vp the verdict to his ſhallow iudgement that there is in euery point well nigh equall probability, but no preſſing certainty. The <hi>iealous</hi> perſon caſts his eye vpon the diſſenting varieties of Doctrines that are in the world, and yet all eagerly defended by learned Patrons: hee obſerues that what one cries vp for an holy truth, an other cries downe for blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous error, that both ſides with confident aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeueration produce and plead their euidences, and withall, that princes and rulers of the earth doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually ſerue their turnes, with either doctrines to manage their affaires, herevpon he is ſuſpitious that there is no conſtant verity in whatſoeuer is propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but that it is for politique ends only, that men haue auouched this or that for truth: or it may bee, becauſe he findes by ſome experience that thoſe vpon whoſe iudgments he hath relyed, haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times deceiued him (though this were his owne fault to take things ſoe ouerhaſtily vpon truſt) yet to eaſe himſelfe, he will vnaduiſedly complaine of that great vncertainty that is in all things, thinking it beſt for the time to come rather to ſuſpend his aſſent, then venture a new coſening: the vpſhot of all is this, that he will be ſo babliſh, as becauſe there is much deceit and ſophiſtication in wares therefore he will conculde no wares are good, or therefore he will buy none: The <hi>contentious</hi> man, who in the pride of his wit glories that he is able to gaineſay whatſoeuer any ſhall averre for true,<note place="margin">Anaxagoras.</note> (for there wanted not an* odde fellow that would croſſe you if you ſaid the ſnow is white) hee at laſt comes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20577:5"/>to be ſo farre tranſported in opinion as to thinke there is nothing but opinion, which you well know falls ſhort of certaine knowledge, and is as the ſchooles ſpeake alwaies <hi>cum formidine oppoſiti</hi> with ſome <hi>ſuſpition</hi> that there may be falſhood in it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> 2a. 2ae. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>artic.</hi> 4.</note> Laſtly there will neuer be wanting the <hi>Impious</hi> perſon, who to finde ſome ſhelter for his irreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to God, &amp; good things, his greateſt enimies, he will as farre as his prophane witte can helpe him, call in queſtion even the firſt and beſt knowne truths; to which improbous labour I ſuppoſe hee much forceth himſelfe, knowing how much it might concerne him, that there were no God to puniſh his villany, no immortality of that ſoule, no reſurrection of that body, that muſt bee reſerued for eternall torments, nor any rule of that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by which he muſt one day bee iudged: but theſe vnworthy conceits are as (more then my hope is) farre from any of you my beloued brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, who haue learnt in the ſchoole of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (herein well deſeruing of humane nature) that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man hath in him that which is accommodate to truth,<note place="margin">Vide Ariſt lib. <hi>1</hi> de moribus ad Eudemum, &amp; lib. <hi>1.</hi> Rhetor. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and that hee is not denyed the finding out of many certainties, nay you haue beene taught in a higher ſchoole, that <hi>truth</hi> (the noble plant that came downe from heauen) <hi>ſhall ſpring out of the earth alſo as Dauid</hi> ſings,<note place="margin">Pſ. 85.11.</note> and that <hi>many ſhall runne too and fro,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>and knowledge</hi> (knowledge not meere opinion) <hi>ſhall bee increaſed</hi>) as ſpeaketh <hi>Daniell.</hi> But this will better appeare when I ſhall ſomewhat open the kinde &amp; nature of that truth whereof our author here treateth. <hi>Solomon</hi> who wrote ſo many
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20577:5"/>bookes euen to <hi>wearineſſe of fleſh</hi> giues this as the <hi>Epitome</hi> of all, <hi>Feare God and keepe his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 12.13.</note> which being the <hi>whole duty of man,</hi> may well be thought the chiefe ſcope of thoſe writings wherein he hath preached to poſterity: more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, for this booke of his <hi>parables,</hi> hee ſalutes his reader in the very entrance with a diſcouery of his full drift, which is,<note place="margin">Prov. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>that men ſhould know wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and instruction, and that they ſhould perceiue the words of vnderſtanding,</hi> now the vnderſtanding he promiſeth, is not (as we may well ſuppoſe) on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of earthly and worldly things, which wee can all well and ſoone enough finde out without the helpe of ſo great a teacher, but of thoſe better, higher matters, belonging to the ſeruice of God the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of ſoules, and the wellfare of all ſocieties, in that great houſe of God, the world. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains then that the <hi>truth</hi> here ſpoken of, ſhould finde an interpretation agreeable to the maine ſcope of the author and conſequently import the true knowledge, which appertaineth to the <hi>true worſhip</hi> of the moſt true God, in whoſe right ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, ſtands the whole duty and felicity of man; Following then this ſenſe, as knowing none other to follow, I muſt a little reſume my former obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſuppoſeth there is ſuch a true knowledge in diuine matters, and that we may bee poſſeſſors thereof, for why ſhould we be ſet to buy that which is not, and to what purpoſe is it, if it may not be bought? herein wee haue the more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>ſcepticks</hi> of our age ſomewhat yealding and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20577:6"/>plyant.<note place="margin">Vide Mont. eſſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi> &amp; Charr. de la ſag. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> For <hi>Montagnie</hi> and <hi>Charron</hi> thoſe two <hi>French</hi> writers that call for ſuch a ſuſpence of iudgments, almoſt in all inferiour things, allowing vs rather to cheapen then buy: yet they willingly grant divine verities, which when reuealed from God, we muſt with ready ſubmiſſion aſſent vnto, as vnto vncontroleable truths. But whether our <hi>Pyrroniſts</hi> euen in faith, will grant ſo much or no, wee will confidently auerre it vpon theſe grounds. <hi>Firſt</hi> wee confeſſe God to be our father and Lord: <hi>now a ſonne honoureth his father, and a ſeruant his Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>as the Prophet Malachy,</hi> but not only by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of prophecy (as I take it) but following herein the very light of nature well inferres. For there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a cloſer ſequence then of theſe termes: <hi>pater, filius, obſequium, dominus, ſervus, hominium,</hi> obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is due from the ſonne to the father, homage from the tenant to his Lord. If then at the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of our being, that bill was drawne whereby we ſtand obliged to God, it is neceſſarily requiſite, that there ſhould be ſome certaine rule of that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which wee owe to him, and that we ſhould be acquainted with it. Our very nature confirmes vs in the acknowledgement that ſuch a truth is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to bee found.<note place="margin">lib 3. cap. 10.</note> For as <hi>Lactantius</hi> well ſhewes, euen by the teſtimony of thoſe, who ſaw nothing but by the twilight of nature, man is naturally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to ſome religious conceits.<note place="margin">lib. <hi>1.</hi> de legibus. Vide Purch. pilgrimag. paſſim.</note> 
               <hi>Philoſophers</hi> haue differenced him from all other creatures by this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, ſo that indeed, as <hi>Cicero</hi> long agoe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and our late nauigations haue plentifully
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20577:6"/>diſcouered, there is not any ſo wild a portion of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind which doth not ſerue ſome deity, ſtriuing to content it with thoſe kinds of worſhips which they hope will be accepted. Is there then this propenſion of all to ſome religion, &amp; is there no religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which may truly ſatiſfie it? Why is our vnderſtanding de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of the knowledg of an infinit truth, if it be not capable thereof, why capable, if there be no way to enioy it? Why doth our will not ſtay it ſelf vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any finite obiect, but is ſtill preſſing forward to an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit goodneſſe, if there be no certaine courſe to bee made partakers thereof. I will firſt beleiue that God giues, and our nature receiues ſo admirable a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty in vaine, before I can be perſwaded that there is no true religion, which only is that which can giue reſt to theſe reſtleſſe appetites of our ſoules. <hi>Adde</hi> in the laſt place that man, a creature of one of the higheſt formes (for he is but little inferiour to the Angells) ſhould bee one of the fooliſheſt and moſt wretched, if religion were meerely but a name or fiction, or if hauing truth in it, could not, poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be poſſeſſed by vs. For as <hi>Ficinus</hi> well ſhewes,<note place="margin">De relig. Chriſt. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> many, as the <hi>Apostles</hi> forſake all things, all men ſomething, out of the loue or feare of a Godhead: we quit preſent things in hope or dread of future, our conſciences are continually exerciſed either in feaſting our ſelues for the obſerued, or vexing our ſelues for the omitted duty to that divine power which we acknowledge: now if all this were vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in vaine, we are moſt vaine and miſerable, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſince wee obſerue in inferiour creatures no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20577:7"/>naturall diſpoſition to abſtaine from preſent good things in expectation of future, or carry themſelues in ſuch a voluntary ſtrictneſſe. We may not, who for want of time muſt bee faine to leaue out ſome thing neceſſary, ſtand too long vpon ſuperfluous matters, &amp; therefore will vpon the premiſes which even nature may ſubſcribe vnto, conclude, that there is ſome where extant a forme of the true worſhip of God, whereof man may bee partaker. But the troublous diſpute of the world is, what this true worſhip is, wherein it conſiſts, where to bee bought, by what meanes to be purchaſed. Let mee haſten then to theſe points, not vnfit for this place, neceſſary I am ſure for theſe times, wherein ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are at a ſtand which way to take, not a few haue turned their backs to that wherein they ought to haue proceeded: and all of vs (God pardon our coldneſſe and faint-heartedneſſe) not ſo forward to vphold and beautify the truth which wee doe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> phraſe of buying, here vſed, ſomewhat di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects vs in our inquiry: for the law of this action is, that wee conſider of the wares that are tendred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. Hee that would haue vs take things becauſe offered, doth not fell but impoſe and tirannize. A man may ſafely ſuſpect his dealing that would haue vs chooſe and winke, or buy in the darke. The <hi>baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of falſhood ſhuns the light, but <hi>truth</hi> as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Lib. cont. valent. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nihil erubeſcit niſi ſolummodo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcondi, is aſhamed of nothing but to be hid:</hi> it calles for all eyes, and feareth not the ſeuereſt tryall; if it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20577:7"/>were onely guilded ouer, it might forbid touching or ſcraping, but being maſſy &amp; ſolid gold through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, the more you handle and examine it the brighter it will appeare. It cannot therefore be but a* <hi>Turciſme</hi> in the Church of Rome,<note place="margin">De Turcarum ſententia vide Lod. Vivem de verit Chriſt. fidei lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> which allowes not the people of God to try before they truſt, but becauſe ſhe findes the ignorance of the moſt to bee her greateſt reuenue ſhakels the ſoules of infinit numbers in the priſon of a darke implicit faith, as if they could not be holy but in ſtupidity, nor good Chriſtians vnleſſe they turne beaſts and bee led without reaſon: but ſhall we with ſuch curious dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ſuruey the nature and conditions of thoſe wares, that are commodious for the body, and ſhall we truſt a few plauſible words of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man &amp; goe no farther, in matters of that moment, as religion is, vpon the truth whereof dependes the ſaluation of our ſoules? Why? Is it not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for men to be men and erre, are not many falſe prophets gone out into the world, are there not many falſhoods for one truth, &amp; doth not falſhood at the firſt bluſh ſometimes, ſeeme as truth? Was there neuer any rotten wood varniſhed or painted, was it neuer knowne that a ſtrumpet put vpon her the attire and geſtures of an honeſt matron? Now how ſhall all this fraud bee diſcouered, if wee will put out our owne eyes and not vſe that diſcretion which God and nature hath left vs for the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of things. I confeſſe indeed that if we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne vp our ſelues, wholy to ſome others opinion and degrade our ſelues of our own vnderſtanding,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20577:8"/>wee may fall vpon ſome truths in the worſhip of God, but this is by chance not iudgement, and is not much better then if we ſhould againe build vp the<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 17.23.</note> 
               <hi>Altar to the vnknown God.</hi> To remedy all theſe inconueniences, let vs embrace the allowance of the bleſſed Apoſtles,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.21.</note> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> who exhorts <hi>vs to try all things and hold that which is good:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn. 4.1.</note> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> who bids vs <hi>not to beleiue every ſpirit but try them whether they are of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.15.</note> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, <hi>that wee be ready alwaies to giue an anſwere to euery man that asketh a reaſon of the hope that is in vs.</hi> This that wee may be able to doe, let vs goe on and ſhew the beſt meanes whereby wee may diſcerne <hi>truth</hi> from <hi>falſhood</hi> in matter of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where firſt it is no reaſon why it ſhould not eaſily be granted, that that is truth which beares conformity to the minde of the firſt truth, God: for our vnderſtanding is no otherwiſe true, then as it is euen and adequate to things themſelues, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering them as they are, nor are thoſe Entitles true but as they are agreeable to diuine vnderſtanding, which is not only the meaſure but the cauſe of all things, but if in any thing certainely in religion that is moſt true, that beares correſpondency with Gods minde and will: for who ſhould preſcribe what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to his honour but himſelfe? Shall man who knowes ſo little in and about himſelfe? (eſpecially ſince his vnderſtanding grew crazie by his fall) at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to define how his maker ſhall bee ſerued? The effect of this preſumption, is too well known
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20577:8"/>in the ſuperſtitious, who meaſuring God by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, thruſt ſuch vnſeemely kindneſſes vpon him as are wholy vnworthy of his maieſty: yea (to ſpeake the truth) worſhip their owne fancies inſteed of a deity: what an ilfauoured and miſhapen peece of honour would it bee, which a ſilly country fellow ſhould lay downe for the right ſervice of our king, &amp; may we not quickly imagine, what an vntoward forme of diuine worſhip, that would proue, which poore ignorant man, a worme &amp; no man deviſeth. No, no, let vs let God alone with his owne honour: he is beſt knowne how great he is to himſelfe, and can ſurely tell vs what his will is, he cannot be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued becauſe moſt wiſe, he will not deceiue, becauſe moſt good. It is by the ſunne that wee behold the ſunne: it muſt be by God himſelfe that wee can know God: and therefore for this point, wee may ſet vp our reſolution <hi>with Ambroſe</hi> in his epiſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Symmachus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. cont. Symmachum.</note> 
               <hi>coeli myſteria doceat me Deus ipſe, qui condidit, non homo qui ſeipſum ignorauit, cui magis de Deo quam Deo credam? As for the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of heauen, let God teach vs who made vs, not man who knowes not himſelfe, concerning God whom ſhould we better truſt then God himſelfe?</hi> That of Saint <hi>Hilary</hi> is of kinne to this,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Trinit.</note> 
               <hi>concedamus cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitionem ſui Deo: idoneus enim ſibi teſtis eſt, qui niſi per ſe cognitus non eſt; let vs leaue</hi> to God the <hi>knowledge of himſelfe, and ſince he is not known but by himſelfe, hee is fittest to be</hi> his owne witneſſe; but let vs with attentiveſt reverence, marke the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of God himſelfe in the prophecy of his ſeruant
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20577:9"/>
               <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 29.14.</note> the words whereof his owne ſonne repeates in the fifteenth of Matthew,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.9.</note> 
               <hi>In vaine doe they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip me teaching for doctrines the commandements of men. Now</hi> ſince the conceit of man, is ſo vaine a meaſure of diuine worſhip, and that God muſt bee honoured after his owne way, it remaines to be but enquired where the ſeate of his will is * <hi>Saluianus</hi> readily anſweres vs,<note place="margin">De guber. mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ip ſum ſacrae ſcripturae oraculum, Dei mens est, the oracle of holy ſcripture is the mind of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 77.17.</note> If it be truth we ſeeke for, <hi>thy word O Father is truth</hi> ſaith our <hi>Sauiour.</hi> Behold the louing care of God to man; when by reaſon of our lame and blinde vnderſtanding wee could not ſoare vp to God, to enter our ſelues into his acquaintance, hee hath deſcended downe to vs; by thoſe who haue beene from euerlaſting in his boſome, his deare ſonne and ſpirit, he hath conveied vnto vs his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.21. <hi>Greg. mag.</hi>
               </note> and by the men who ſpake and wrote as they were inſpired, hath ſent vs (as <hi>Gregories</hi> phraſe is) diverſe <hi>epiſtles</hi> concerning his will: here then may we reſt, that whatſoeuer his word enioineth, is well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing, whatſoeuer it forbiddeth is vnacceptable to him, whatſoeuer is of a middle nature, it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine whether it may be wellcome; It is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is not expected. They are then too daring that thruſt vpon the people of God, as neceſſary to their ſaluation or their makers worſhip, thoſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruances, that we are ſure are beſide, they are not ſure are not againſt this written word. If it were poſſible in theſe contentious times, for any one man of an humble and indifferent ſpirit, no more
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20577:9"/>to heare of thoſe differences of religion, which ſo much troubles the world, then that good poore man in the ſtory of* <hi>Alexander</hi> did of thoſe wars that had filled all <hi>Aſia</hi> in his time,<note place="margin">Vide Curtium in lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and had beene long round about him, before hee had diligently read ouer the holy ſcriptures, and if afterwards there ſhould without all foreſtalling perſwaſions or Oratory inference be nakedly layd downe the articles of our doctrine and the tenents of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Church, it were not poſſible but he ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the ſweet conſent, which our religion hath with Gods word, and he would more then wonder from whence all the reſt were fetcht, and would conclude that if what they teach in many points, be true, there hath crept into the world a new Goſpell, whereof no footſteps in the many writings of the holy Prophets and Apoſtles doe appeare. Theſe additaments are ſtiled ſacred traditions, but by what chaine were they let downe from heauen? Or how can their neceſſary vſe by prudent hearted chriſtians bee embraced, when they are already bound to beleiue,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>that the Scriptures are able to make vs wiſe vnto ſaluation</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, and <hi>that they are of ſufficiency for all thoſe things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the man of God may be perfectly furniſhed to euery good worke:</hi> men may bee wiſe aboue that which is written, but then they are wiſe aboue ſobriety; for it is a luxury in religion to deſire more, then what will inſtruct vs to every good worke here and fit vs for eternall ſaluation hereafter.</p>
            <p>But here wee muſt goe one ſtep farther to quit
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20577:10"/>that obiection which good ſoules, doe many times make againſt their owne good; for they willingly granting that God hath made the ſcripture a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect regiſter of his will, and that it is a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to man, that God himſelfe is become his teacher, by whom if he bee deceiued he may ſay as he of old,<note place="margin">Rich. de So vict.</note> 
               <hi>Si erròr è Domine a te decepti ſumus, if I am in an error thy word hath deceiued me;</hi> yet how ſhall theſe writings bee vnderſtood by vs? For wee heare many and thoſe none of the meaneſt clerkes, complaining of the great obſcurity to be found in that booke, and how ſhall wee <hi>Puiſnes</hi> and <hi>Pigmes</hi> in compariſon of others reach to the ſence thereof; buy the truth we would, but it is ſomewhat aboue the proportion of our ſtates and abilities: to this I can giue no better anſwere, but doe yee with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diligence and teachable affections read ouer this heauenly booke and you will anſwere your ſelues: for doubtleſſe you ſhall finde many eaſy places therein, and thoſe will incourage you to read the reſt. Euen this writing of <hi>Solomon</hi> though it containe parables high enough for the moſt reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnderſtanding, yet withall it certifies vs in the very* entrance <hi>that they are framed to giue ſubtilty to the ſimple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>and to the young man knowledge and diſcretion;</hi> and will the ſpirit faile of the end pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed? Experience will teach vs otherwife, for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we ſhall meete in ſcriptures with ſome of thoſe depths wherein <hi>Eiephants</hi> may ſwimme, and if they will bee too curiouſly and preſumptuouſly venturing, be drowned too; yet we ſhall alſo light
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20577:10"/>vpon exceeding many foords, and thoſe ſtreaming likewiſe with the waters of life, wherein thoſe that are yet but lambes may wade and be refreſhed; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable is the temper of holy ſcriptures, as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor thereof takes care of all and is <hi>rich to all that call vpon him</hi> as ſpeakes the <hi>Apostle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.12.</note> ſo is the ſtile thereof diſpoſed and bending towards all, that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach with reuerence: it ſo exerciſeth the wits of the moſt learned, as that it ſatiſfieth the deſires of the moſt ignorant: God is the Father and lord of vs all, and he ſpeakes as becometh both thoſe titles; for hauing differing children and ſeruants and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving commandes for all of them, he muſt needs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper his ſpeech to each ſeuerall capacity, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one may know his duty in the place hee holds vnder him.<note place="margin">Vide Vivem de verit. fidei lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap: de virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus evangelii.</note> Howſoeuer then the olde <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſavouring of the heatheniſh envy and pride, and mindeing onely the benefit of a few, profeſſe they will write obſcurely, and to the moſt as good as if they wrote not at all,<note place="margin">Ariſt. epiſt. ad Alexandrum de libris phyfic. auſcult.</note> witneſſe the epiſtle of <hi>Airist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otle</hi> to his greateſt ſcholler, yet to conceiue ſo of God, the author of <hi>mankind,</hi> aſwell as of the <hi>Bible,</hi> were the impeachment of his wiſdome and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for what ſhall he be the God onely of <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities,</hi> ſhall the witty onely ingroſſe him? No,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 20.28.</note> doubtleſſe hee is a God of the* <hi>vallies</hi> as well as of the <hi>mountaines</hi> &amp; the ſhowres of his gratious plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſhall equally deſcend on both: there are in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery corner of his family ſoules ſicke, and to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; hungry and to be fed; naked and to be clothed loſt and to be found, and therefore there is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20577:11"/>in his word, that medicine, meat, ſuccor, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, that ſhall bee fit for all, there is a ſpirituall market where all may buy: but heere is the folly, we are many of vs lazy, and then lay our ſloth vpon obſcurity of ſcriptures, and ſome of vs it may bee drunke with inordinate affections, and then like drundards though the way bee broad and plaine inough yet we find fault with the narrowneſſe &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euenneſſe; yea by the abuſe of our ſelues and the word of God, inſtead of buying his truth wee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe that his grieuous iudgement, <hi>that ſeeing wee ſhall not ſee, and hearing wee ſhall not vnderſtand,</hi> that ſo that of the Apoſtle may bee verified:<note place="margin">Mat. 13.14. 2 Cor. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>if the Goſpell bee hid it is hid vnto them that periſh, in whom the God of this world hath blinded their mindes, that the light of the glorious Goſpell of Chriſt ſhould not ſhine vnto them.</hi> Much fault may bee in our ſelues, that wee miſſe of ſo rich a bargaine as truth; but came wee with honeſt mindes to the word, we ſhould finde, that though many hard things therein ſurpaſſe our vnderſtanding, yet if we practiſe, but ſo many duties of piety, and embrace ſo many articles of faith, which wee may clearely vnderſtand, there will remaine of eaſy leſſons ſuch ſtore, as ſhall ſerue to the attainment of eternall life. Thus haue wee layd downe the prime and maſter direction how to deſcerne falſhood from that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly truth which we would buy; ſhewing that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to be retained as neceſſary to the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, which beares not conformity to his will, whereof the letters patents are the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20577:11"/>but further, becauſe in the ware it ſelfe, which we would get into our hand, there are found certaine proper qualities or characters whereby it may be diſtinctly knowne from ſophiſticate falſhoods, it will not be impertinent to admoniſh ſomewhat herein.</p>
            <p>The firſt innate property of this truth, is that it is alway one and the ſame, euen as God himſelfe the parent thereof is, <hi>in whom is no variableneſſe or ſhadowe of turning ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iac. 1.17. Eph. 4.5.</note> as <hi>one</hi> Lord ſo <hi>one</hi> faith, is S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paules</hi> doctrine; to imagine that diuers and contrary traditions in religion may be true, is to bring in a plurality of Gods. For the one and ſimple vnderſtanding of one God, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly caſt forth the beames of two truths. Well then may <hi>Auſten</hi> call that opinion of <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de haereſ. cap. <hi>72.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>haereſin nimium mirabilis vanitatis, an hereſy of a prodigious vanity,</hi> who held that all here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques though of neuer ſo different fancies, did yet ſpeake the truth, as if any thing could ſwarue from it ſelfe and remaine it ſelfe; no, no, truth is more vniforme and conſtant, inſomuch that if we ſuruey all the parcels of this rich &amp; beautifull commodity, we ſhall finde each ſeuerall to agree with the reſt in admirable conſent; whereas if wee take into our hands the infinite peeces of falſhood, wee ſhall not onely perceiue them oppoſite to truth, but incohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent one to another, nay in the ſame cauſe or queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion it will not be hard to deſcry the premiſſes, and the more removed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequences mutually to wound one another and be both falſe; but truth cuts not her owne throat, but rather each part of her (if of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20577:12"/>ſo partleſſe a thing I may ſo ſpeake) lends ſtron ſuccour to the other.</p>
            <p>The ſecond natiue note of diuine truth is, that it ſtill reflects it ſelfe vpon the glory of its Author, and therefore ſhe, as wiſdome in the booke of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs,</hi> gets her to the <hi>top of the high places,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8.2.3. Pſal. 29.1.2.</note> ſhee ſtands at euery entrance and ſings that <hi>Pſalme</hi> with a chearefull voice, <hi>Giue vnto the Lord O yee mighty, giue vnto the Lord Glory and strength, giue vnto the Lord the glory due vnto his name:</hi> all her cry is that fleſh and blood may be humbled, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſpirits glorified: ſhe bids miſerable man at laſt know and acknowledge his miſery, and begin to confeſſe himſelfe altogether vnworthy of the leaſt of his provoked makers mercy: ſhe preaceth to him, not to ſtand vpon the prerogatiues of naturall goodneſſe, ſhee counſelleth him to caſt away the inſolent conceit of his owne merits and ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and rely onely vpon the free and vndeſerued grace of God for his ſaluation: ſhee commandes him to ſubmit all his owne wiſdome, greatneſſe, power, to the power, greatneſſe, wiſdome of God: ſhe inioines him not to take in any partners into his redeemers honour, but to let him haue all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his owne workes without a ſharer: this voice thus aduancing our creator and reſtorer, is high &amp; true; but when I heare a skreaking, that I am not ſo poore but that doeing what I may doe, by my depraued nature, I deſerue at leaſtwiſe in congrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that God ſhould looke favourably vpon mee, &amp; when his fauour is receiued, I then can doe thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20577:12"/>works which by their owne proper dignity, may merit heauen and bring God vnder a debt: when I heare a noiſe that I muſt get mee ſome of the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings of other mens goodneſſe, or pay ſome of mine owne ſatiſfactions to helpe out the merits of my ſaviour (as if there were ſome want in him of <hi>whoſe fulnſſe wee may all receiue grace for grace</hi>) when I am ſollicited in performance of religion,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.16.</note> to doe beſides and ſometimes againſt the command of God, as if I might be a thought wiſer then my maker: theſe ſounds muſt needs bee vntuneable to truth, ſince they ſet not forth the grace and glory of God in that higheſt ſtrain, which heauenly doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines ſhould reach vnto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly</hi> if amongſt a heape of fruitleſſe &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe doctrines that vſually lye vpon the ſtall, we would finde out and buy the truth, let vs enquire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that which containes the moſt certaine and ſafe method of our reconciliation with God: for ſince religion (as that noble <hi>Frenchman</hi> hath it) <hi>is the art of ſauing man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mornaeus de verit. rel. Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anae. cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> which cannot bee but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction with God, and ſince it is confeſſed on all hands, that ſinne hath made a great gulfe betwixt God and man; that muſt needs bee the only truth, which will tell vs how a friendſhip may bee made vp againe betwixt the creator and his creature, hence ſome ſay <hi>religion</hi> takes his name, becauſe it doth<note n="*" place="margin">Vide Lactant. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>28.</hi> &amp; Aug. de civ. dei. l. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>relige</hi> or binde together againe what was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily diſvnited. But be that as <hi>Grammarians</hi> can agree, it will be agreed by diuines, that all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ſhould be vtterly loſt, if being by ſin brought
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20577:13"/>vnto the very margent of that bottomles helliſh pit, there ſhould be no bridge appointed, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh vs ouer in ſafety to the mercies of heauen, but herein the grace of God, (which the ſcripture hath the honour to publiſh helps by bringing vs cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine newes of an <hi>Emmanuella God-man, a media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,</hi> who by his infinitely meritorious ſufferings (for what cannot the blood of the ſon of God ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine) payd off all the ſcores of his Fathers iuſtice, extinquiſhed all the fiery fierceneſſe of his wrath and reconciled vs to his euerlaſting loue, wherein is euerlaſting life and health: <hi>when we were enimies</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>wee were reconciled to God by the death of his ſonne, and being reconciled, we ſhall bee ſaued by his life.</hi> This is a true ſaying and worthy by all meanes to bee receiued, becauſe it can onely giue aſſurance of peace to our troubled conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whereas all other waies in the caſe of mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God, are but as thinne, rotten, ſhort threads, applyed to the bowing of a mighty <hi>Cedar,</hi> to a poore ſhrubbe of wonderfull great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from it, euen tyes and bandes weaker and vainer then vanity itſelfe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it may paſſe for an indiuiduall marke of true religion, that it is a leader to true ſanctity <hi>The wiſdome that is from aboue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iac. 3.17.1.27.</note> 
               <hi>is first pure?</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iames,</hi> and in the laſt verſe of his firſt chapter <hi>hee giues this character</hi> thereof, <hi>charity towards others and cleaneſſe in our ſelues.</hi> Not that all profeſſors of the truth, are preſently poſſeſſed with ſanctity, not that the ſanctity which is in the beſt, is in this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20577:13"/>life perfectly ſquared to the exact rule of truth; but our meaning is, that what is diuinely true doth in its owne nature neceſſarily tend to the purging of our ſoules from corruption, and the introducing of holy innocency, charity and euery other vertue: It muſt needs bee ſo, ſince truth is the daughter of God, the <hi>Holy of holies;</hi> when therefore we heare a doctrine that fauours our ſenſuality, that giues diſpenſation to carnall liberty, that lendes patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage to the fopperies of our time, <hi>vt honeste pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re videamur,</hi> that we may ſeeme honeſtly vaine; The voice thereof, bewraies the falſhood of it, nay it is a very vnlucky truth (if any truth can haue that miſfortune) which when entertained moues no man the more to the loue of God or practiſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny goodneſſe. In a word ſince it was wiſely ſaid, <hi>Summa religionis eſt imitari quem colis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>it is the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brigement of all religion to imitate him whom a man worſhips:</hi> it is but froth, that is not able to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print in our accompts the liuely reſemblance of that holineſſe which is in God. If it cannot beget vertue but ſerues only to make vs hide our bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it hath but the force of an humane law; if it doe but onely pare off, but not root vp vices, it is but a lecture of heathenniſh philoſophy: if inſtead of croſſing, it gratifies the ill humours of the fleſh, and world, it is the doctrine of divells; but if it bee fitted to the rendring of a man, not onely a full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncer of his owne luſts but a ſincere imitator of his makers holineſſe, this is the truth, that is fallen downe from heauen, to bring vs vp thither.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:20577:14"/>
            <p> Fiftly I muſt adioiyne this, as a cogniſance of the beſt religion, that it calls eſpecially for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man: for nothing can be more agreeable to a ſpirituall and inuiſible nature, then a ſpirituall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: <hi>ſurely the Father ſeekes ſuch worſhippers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.23.</note> as ſpeakes the ſonne, and I hope many ſuch hee will finde, though I cannot but feare there will bee ſtill more, who ſuppoſing that God loues, whatſoeuer they themſelues admire, &amp; going about to put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him their owne humors, place all religion in externall gawdes and ſhewes, what a deale of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>channicall religion, is there in the world whileſt the <hi>Phariſaicall Iew</hi> is buſy in the waſhing of his cupps, and platters,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.25.14.</note> and makes his obſerued prayers long euen to hoarſneſſe, but to haue a cleane and ſincere ſoule is his leaſt care. The <hi>blind heathen</hi> playes the <hi>Antique</hi> in geſture before his God,<note place="margin">Lact. Lib. 4. c. 3.</note> and when his ceremony is ended, his religion is ended. The ſilly <hi>Papiſt</hi> with his fingers turnes ouer his beades, with his knees creeps to his image, with his tongue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes his confeſſors taske, and then he hath done with God till the next holy day: nay whileſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny amongſt our ſelues meere <hi>Mimicks</hi> in religion, are zealous rather in their eyes, eares, hands, tongues, then in their hearts, that finde all religion in the temple, and in the temple leaue it as they finde it, neither bringing in nor carrying away any in their mindes, which ſhould be the hourely liuing Temples of God, beautified with modeſty perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with innocency, and ſtored with the ſacrifices of flagrant loue to God, his cauſes, his ſeruants:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20577:14"/>ſeruices of the body were decent, haue their place, but not as diſtinctiue notes of a true religion, which rather calls for the offices of a good and well guided minde.</p>
            <p>Laſtly I may not omit without wronging my wares, that the truth which muſt be bought, will be knowen by her antiquity and laſtingneſſe, becauſe it is the of ſpring of him <hi>that was, and is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>and is to come:</hi> heere thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will bee ready to pleade a purchaſe, nameing vs <hi>Popes</hi> and aunceſtors for many yeares, in whoſe hands their doctrine hath bin kept, wee deny it not to bee too olde, and yet wee graunt it not to be olde inough: for antiquity hath its degrees; we yeeld the ſecond, but the firſt is the beſt, and that is ours, wee ſay not this or that <hi>Pope</hi> but with <hi>Ignatius Chriſt is our anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delph.</note> nor to vſe <hi>Cyprians Apologie,</hi> doe wee ſo much attende, what any others before vs, haue done or taught,<note n="*" place="margin">Epi. 63.</note> 
               <hi>ſed quid, qui ante omnes eſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus prior fecerit, what Christ who was before them all did, and commanded to be taught and done;</hi> and this truth which in the <hi>Primitiue</hi> times was cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſed and in the darker daies of <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme</hi> preſerued, both in the <hi>Oracles</hi> of the vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted word, and in the hearts of perſecuted wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, our eyes (eyes bleſſed if thankfull) behold it, not <hi>new</hi> but <hi>renewed,</hi> and vindicated from the tirannie of former times, if it had ſtood onely vpon humane props; fraudes and forces might by this time haue vndermined it, but by a higher hand, it hath hitherto miraculouſly continued, and no
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20577:15"/>doubt will to the end of all things; ſince there is no reaſon why God who is if I may ſo ſpeake as wiſe at firſt as at laſt, and as ſtrong at laſt as at firſt, ſhould either change his minde or not afford his ſupport.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus ſhewed where truth is ſhopt, and how it may be diſcouered the onely labour that is left mee, is, to ſtirre you vp to bee ſo affected that it may be poſſeſſed by you: where not to bee ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant as to chalke you out a way of ſtudy in arts and ſciences, and languages, and ſuch like helps, to the inquiſition euen of divine truths, this I leaue to the <hi>Gamaliels</hi> &amp; maiſters of the <hi>Iſraell</hi> at whoſe feet I wiſh I might haue longer ſate. I ſhall onely accompt it my duty, to admoniſh you and my ſelfe in a few words of the chiefeſt <hi>qualities</hi> wherewith wee ſhould bee inueſted, who are inioyned to buy the truth.</p>
            <p>And here let a high loue and eſteeme of this ware be firſt wrought in vs: for doubtleſſe here is a thing of rich value before vs, ſince the holy ghoſt doth ſo ſollicite vs to the purchaſing thereof, wee may well giue it out, that this is that one <hi>pearle of great price mentioned</hi> in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13.46.</note> 
               <hi>which cauſed the wiſe merchant to goe and ſell all that he had and buy it,</hi> for if it be an excellency, drawing toward <hi>Angellicall</hi> perfection, to conſider of things as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are: if it be ſo ſweet a food to the ſoule of man to contemplate of thoſe matters whereof ſhe is capable without miſtakeing: if it bee the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt ſchollerſhip to coppy out into our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, that which is originally &amp; eternally in Gods:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20577:15"/>if God bee ſo iealous of his honour, and ſo vnlike thoſe ſo ciable Gods of the heathen, that one only preſcribed worſhip can content him; how ſhould wee bee rauiſhed with truth in which all this is found, wee cannot but long to buy it, if wee once bee thus perſwaded of the worth of it.</p>
            <p>Therefore I hope the next thing will bee heeded by vs, which is, as heartily to be affected with the excellency of ſcriptures, aboue all other writings, ſince in that holy paper is vnqueſtionably wrapt vp this heauenly ware;<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.19.</note> much time would then bee ſpent as was done by <hi>Timothy in knowing the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred letters,</hi> and not ſuffer our ſelues to bee ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched with the name of humane polite literature, that <hi>Philoſophers, Hiſtorians, Poets,</hi> yea and thoſe <hi>Diuines</hi> too, with whom <hi>Aristotle</hi> is more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent then <hi>Paule,</hi> ſhould take vp our ſolemneſt, and devouteſt ſtudies, and the <hi>Bible</hi> bee onely read at ſome by houres, rather becauſe we would not bee altogether ignorant, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that we would be very skil full in it: ſurely they are worthy to bee deceiued in diuine matters, who are infected with the humour of <hi>Angelus Palitianus</hi> who would not vouchſafe the reading of ſcriptures,<note place="margin">Vide viuem de veri. fidei lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. de veter. Teſtam.</note> as not containeing ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies ſutable to his wit and ſtile, as if he meant to be ſaued by <hi>Criticiſmes and quainter phraſes.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi> bewailes this vanity of his,<note place="margin">lib <hi>3.</hi> conf. cap. <hi>5</hi>
               </note> with whom whileſt not conuerted <hi>Tully</hi> aboue all compares ſeemed worthier of his ſtudy, then any of our inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red authors, we may think it a malady of great wits
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20577:16"/>which had need to be cured by ſuch repentance; let good wits therefore take heede of it.</p>
            <p>Now as we loue truth and the records of it, ſo if we would ſtore our ſelues therewith, I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more neceſſary then to come with honeſt and purged affections: for a minde blurred with ſenſuall vanities, worldly corruptions, diueliſh wickedneſſe, can hardly take the faire impreſſions of truth.<note place="margin">Sap. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>Into a malicious ſoule wiſdome (as it is in the booke of Wiſdome) ſhall not enter nor dwell in the body that is a ſubiect vnto ſinne,</hi> If pride be the domineering ſinne in vs,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and hath giuen vs any of the <hi>waters of strife</hi> to drinke, Lord, how hard wee ſtudy, yet not to buy but diſgrace a truth: if it hath bin our ill lucke to haue vented an errour, wee take it our credit to defend it, and though wee are conſcious of the falſhood yet wee muſt not ſeeme to erre: In our conferences which ſhould ſerue to put vp truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, it is victory that is onely aimed at. A mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt man dares ſcarce ſpeake what is true for feare of putting vs into the contrary error: and as the leauen of pride is ſo ſoure, ſo is it wonderfully ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as if plaine and certaine truths were <hi>occupata materia,</hi> a matter already taken vp by others of low and vulgar wits, and vnfit for the ſublimity of our ſpirits: we range after curious ſpeculations that ſtill will runne away from vs, or if caught will bee of no vſe: wee peremptorily determine where wee ſhould onely religiouſly admire, againe, if this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit haunt vs, a new error pleaſeth vs better then an auncient eſtabliſhed truth, thinking it a brauer act
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20577:16"/>to be the maiſter of a young vanity, then the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of an aged truth, no wonder then if ſome, now and then, picke out of their authors ſuch a point for their venting, which others ſaw as well as they, and could haue bought it; but being but a toy and not worth the expence, haue wiſely ſcorned it, theſe marketings can hardly bee avoided by men of pride, humility is more thirſty and ſtill on the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hand; becauſe indeed bleſſed bee him, who as hee fruſtrats proud wits,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.15. Ψ. 25.9.</note> ſo hath hee promiſed <hi>that the humble he will teach his way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as the fate of pride is, ſo is that of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, ſo is that of ſenſuality, ſo is that of enuy, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is that of vncharitableneſſe; all theſe hang plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets vpon the ſoule, &amp; ſuffer her not to aſcend vp to many truths; nay though our vnderſtandings be ſometimes of their owne naturall vigour ſoaring, yet as the very <hi>Eagles</hi> made for ſtight, can onely flutter, not mount when weighty ſtones are tyed to their feet; ſo theſe baſe and vnworthy affections cannot chooſe but clogge and preſſe vs, when wee are to raiſe vp our ſpirits to any high point: but did wee carry in our breaſts, contented, chaſt, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate peaceable affections, indeavouring nothing more then, <hi>to be holy as God is holy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.16.</note> the eye of our ſoules would oft ſee more cleerely &amp; pearce more deepely into heauenly miſteries: that rule of our Sauiour is moſt diuine:<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.17.</note> 
               <hi>If any man will doe the will of my father, he ſhall knowe of the doctrine whether it be of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much here might bee added concerning thoſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20577:17"/>many preiudices whereof wee ſhould alſo rid our ſelues, before we can entertaine truth; it is true it is true, is the cry of many, but why, it is attended with ſignes:<note place="margin">Mat. 24.24.</note> yea but <hi>falſe prophets ſhall doe wonders euen to the deceiuing of the elect themſelues, if that were poſsible:</hi> it is confirmed by the ſufferings of the profeſſors:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yea but 'tis not the <hi>paine but the cauſe that maketh a martyr:</hi> it is accompanied with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity: yea but the Apoſtles &amp; that church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the faith was moſt purely kept,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.37.</note> were <hi>deſtitute, afflicted, tormented:</hi> it is followed by multiudes, yea but it was neuer ſo well with the world <hi>that the beſt thing ſhould pleaſe the moſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 7.13.</note> &amp; the <hi>broad way heares ill:</hi> it is bequeathed by our aunceſtors: <hi>but walke not in the statutes of your fathers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 20.18.</note> I am the <hi>Lord ſaith God ſometimes by his prophets:</hi> it were ill with truth if a long cuſtome could preſcribe againſt it: it is taught by great <hi>Rabbies:</hi> but they liſt not to be men, nor euer could produce any character that exempts them from ignorance: it is deliuered by thoſe of reputed ſanctity: yea but our ſauiour men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth falſe prophets <hi>that ſhall come in ſheepes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.15.</note> nor is I will not ſay a <hi>counſell</hi> of Saints but men, a <hi>quire</hi> of Angells to bee welcomed with any other curteſy then a <hi>curſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>if they bring things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what hath bin receiued from Chriſt.</hi> I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at our ſottiſhneſſe that can bee patient to haue our vnderſtanding giued by theſe weake preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: that we may breake them, let vs be perſwaded of this eaſy truth:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.24.</note> that none but God can <hi>Lord</hi> it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faith: becauſe he alone is ſet aboue errour and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20577:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>deceit: the <hi>Apostle</hi> ſaith it vpon deliberation what <hi>Dauid</hi> did in haſt, <hi>euery man is a lyar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.4. Pſ. 116.11.</note> what through Ignorance, what through negligence: what through malice; ſmall reaſon haue wee then to prime our conſciences vpon any one ſleeue, not knowing whether he will runne with them.</p>
            <p>To auoide all theſe impediments to the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of truth, let vs in the laſt place commend pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vnto you: by which <hi>holy</hi> men haue confeſſed that they haue more profited then by reading, hearing,<note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>112.</hi>
               </note> or any other diligence:<note place="margin">Iob. 32.8.</note> for if it be true what <hi>Elihu</hi> ſaith, <hi>there is a ſpirit in man, but it is the inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lord that giueth vnderſtanding:</hi> and it being moſt true what our ſauiour hath, that <hi>his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will giue the ſpirit to thoſe that aske him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 11.13.</note> who can doubt but that devout prayer is one of the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranteſt coines, whereby wee may traffique with God, for the obtaining of thoſe illuminations that ſhall bring truth with them into our breaſts.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I (reuerent Fathers and bretheren) brought you what I haue conceiued in this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I am not much acquainted with your eares and therefore know not how to fit them: onely I thought that a diſcourſe of truth, and the purchaſe of it, might not be vnſutable to that place wherein is held ſo famous a <hi>Mart</hi> of truth: or did the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations of mine owne meanneſſe deterre mee, ſince I knew I came amongſt the wiſe, with whom as <hi>Proſpers</hi> phraſe is, <hi>truth is not then onely great, when great ones teach it.</hi> But if you will except,<note place="margin">Vide Proſp. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat. in <hi>2.</hi> l. de vita contempl.</note> wee need no encouragement in this kind, for wee
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20577:18"/>haue bought truth already then I haue nothing to ſay but this, euermore defend it with your tongue and penne, and if need bee ſeale it with your blood: euer more adorne it with the holineſſe, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of your liues, that ſo when this life ſhall bee changed into a better, you may with ſoules full of truth the more comfortably come into the preſence of the God of truth, to whom Father, ſonne and holy ghoſt bee aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all glory and praiſe now &amp; for euer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:20577:18"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IAMES I. VER. 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Doe not erre my beloued brethren.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F error were only the diſeaſe of the ignorant, it might reaſonably bee ſaid vnto me, <hi>Phyſition heale thine owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try flocke,</hi> &amp; come not hither where various learning hath provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſufficient preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues againſt this euill, or if this malady of the ſoule, might be cured by a bare information of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the matter more conueniently might bee left to your publicke ſchooles, or priuate ſtudies, then brought vp into your pulpit, but ſince experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence abundantly teacheth, that the moſt dangerous, and troubleſome errors haue had their birth; and breeding amidſt the tongues, and pens, of men famed for their wit &amp; learning; and ſince the affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions, (which many times are as inordinate in the greateſt clerks, as the ſimpleſt Idiots) doe (though very irregularly I confeſſe) too too oft lead the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20577:19"/>vnderſtanding: I could not take it ſo misbeſeeming a worke for a preacher, who hath ſo much to doe with the ordering of mens affections, to take in hand this ſubiect in this place, let mee then once more (Reuerent Fathers &amp; beloued brethren) ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vpon your patience, and as heretofore I haue from that <hi>wiſe king</hi> invited you to <hi>buy the truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 23.23.</note> ſo ſuffer mee now from this <hi>holy Apostle</hi> adviſe you <hi>to fly error.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A thing</hi> (if yet I can entitle it to <hi>entity</hi>) well worth our ſpeedieſt flying from it, or chaſing it from vs.<note place="margin">Errorem defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refacilius quam finire Aug. lib. <hi>1.</hi> contra Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micos cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> For if wee define error, <hi>which is ſooner defined then finiſhed</hi> ſaid <hi>Licentius,</hi> what is it but a pittifull deformity, &amp; incongruity betwixt our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and the things which God and nature haue eſtabliſhed? For as it is the iuſtice of truth to conſider euery thing as indeed it is, herein nobly doing right to the firſt truth, God (the fountaine of that ſetled being which things haue) ſo on the contrary iniurious error is a falſe witnes-bearer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, reporting otherwiſe of things, then God made them, or then hee would haue them to bee apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by vs; either faſtning vpon things what belongs not to them, or denying to them what doth. Alas how haue we loſt God, and the tracks of things as he hath left them to vs, yea how haue wee loſt our ſelues, and the indowments where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee were truſted! For whereas reaſon was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon vs, to be a lamp whereby we might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne betwixt truth, and that which is the ſhadow thereof, error hath put out this light, and ſo depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20577:19"/>vs of that which is <hi>the ſoule of the ſoule</hi> to vſe <hi>Philo</hi> his words <hi>euen as the apple is the eye of the eye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De mundi opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio.</note> 
               <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſpeake of a naturall appetite which the ſoule of euery man hath to know what is true in things; &amp; therefore howſoeuer there may be found thouſands, that moſt gladly would deceiue others, ſcarce one among them would willingly be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued himſelfe. Yet I know not how error hath ſomewhat dulled this appetite, I am ſure it cannot ſatiſfie it, but fruſtrates the honeſt deſires of the ſoule; and inſteed of her due meate, feeds her either with incertaine opinions which breed crude, and vndigeſted tenents in the iudgement, or elſe with certaine falſhood the very poyſon of the minde. Nor is error only dangerous to the firſt harborers of it, but like the plauge, it runns from man to man; no man almoſt being content to erre to himſelfe, but hath a longing to tranſmit his erronious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits to others, as it appeareth in all Hereticks. But the malignity of error is neuer of greater force then when it lighteth into men of our calling, for when we haue once loſt part of our prieſtly <hi>pectorall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod</hi> 28.30.</note> our <hi>vrim</hi> our light of true doctrine, and haue clad our ſelues in the darke hue of falſhood, wee conueigh our faſhion vnto multitude of ſoules, and cannot periſh alone. By this you ſee the perrill, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but welcome our Apoſtles admonition, calling you from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> then is an admonition in this kinde, ſo much the more to be heeded, the fouler the error is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which the warning is giuen. Such a one is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20577:20"/>this which Saint <hi>Iames</hi> meanes; for if you will ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh the verſes bordering vpon my text, you ſhall finde him labouring to root that impiouſly abſurd conceit out of mens minds <hi>that God is a ſollicitor and temptor to ſinne,</hi> The diuell greedy after the deſtruction of ſoules, was it ſeems impatient of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny long delay, ere hee wrought his feates, and therefore not tarrying vntill the Goſpell of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour were generally planted and ſtrongly rooted in mens hearts by the preaching of the apoſtles, hee very early began to ſow his tares, where the Lords firſt husband men had caſt in their good ſeed. Nay ſo diligent was the malice of Satan, in his hireling <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> the <hi>Patriarch of hereticks,</hi> that the <hi>Apostles</hi> were prevented,<note place="margin">Haeretic. Fabul. compend. de Simone.</note> for as <hi>Theodoret</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when he had quitted Samaria, he trauelled into diuers parts, where the Apoſtles had not preached, foreſtalling as he went along the mindes of men, with his deteſtable impoſtures, that the doctrine of Apoſtolicall teachers, might wholly bee ſhut out, or enter with greater difficulty; now among his peſtilentiall errors,<note place="margin">Aduerſ. haereſes cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> that was one, as <hi>Vincentius</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, that God <hi>the creator was author of the euills, euen of ſinne;</hi> an impiety which wanted not abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in all ages; For beſides <hi>Simon, Cerdon, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, Florinus</hi> in the firſt times, and the <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees,</hi> with the <hi>Priſcillianists,</hi> afterwards, euen our preſent age hath afforded that impure ſect of the <hi>Libertines</hi> fouly guilty that way. It is probable that ſome in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time had drunk of <hi>Simons</hi> cuppe, which might moue Saint <hi>Iames</hi> to giue ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veats
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20577:20"/>to his ſchollers, that they erre not in this point: Howſoeuer we deeme of the occaſion, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him to write, his admonition, is ſo much the waightier, the more grieuous the error which hee ſpeakes of, is: an error <hi>primae magnitudinis</hi> of the biggeſt ſize. For if God be an author of, or a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſinfull euill; if wee cannot bee content to ſay that he permits offences, but will haue him to neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate them; if wee cannot reſt ſatiſfied with that truth, that God doth in his infinit wiſdome make vſe of the wicked wills of his creatures, to his owne glory, but wee will further ſay that hee makes their wills ſo wicked; if when men are read to be hardned by God, wee will pronounce that hee doth it, not only by witholding grace, but infuſing mallice: if when wee ſpeake of Gods concurring, with euery worke of his creature, wee will not diſtinguiſh the action it ſelfe from the obliquity, but promiſcuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entitle God to both: Lord what confuſion will there be in all things, let the pale betwixt iuſt and vniuſt, holy and prophane be pull'd downe! For if God ſolicit and impell men to evill, when I ſinne I ſin not, for why ſhould it be my fault to bee lead by God, nay this confounds God and the diuell make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them all one; then which what more horrid blaſphemy can be conceaued. And as for the attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of God, which are indeed himſelfe, not one of them can ſtand with any honor, if this error bee not demoliſhed; for how is he goodneſſe it ſelfe if ſuch ſtreames of euill doe flow from him, how is he all power when he is the parent of defects, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencies?
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20577:21"/>What iuſtice is it to puniſh thoſe crimes which he himſelfe makes, and plague in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother his owne fault; and if he encline, yea driue a man to ſinne, that ſo afterwards he may ſhew his mercy in remitting it,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> alas, as that father ſaith it is but a <hi>maleuolent good will</hi> to make any one miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to appeare himſelfe mercifull. A more ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious indignity againſt God cannot bee offered, then by this abominable error; not is there any more pernitious to humane ſociety. For it erects a prophane ſanctuary for all offenders, euery one ſheltring his iniquity, vnder the authority &amp; patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of God himſelfe. There is in man a naturall humour not to owne his offences, and he is glad if he can tranſlate them vpon another; this error af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords the boldeſt ſhift, when it propoſeth God the author of and mouer to ſinns, none if this doctrine were currant, but would freely and riotouſly offend when they haue not fault, but neceſſity, yea diuine authority to charge in whatſoeuer they doe. This I ſpeake to diſcouer the waight of the Apoſtles ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, who giues warning in a matter of great importance, this error not only grating vpon, but caſting downe the very foundation of all religion.</p>
            <p>But although our Apoſtle hath eſpeciall refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to this one particular moſt impious error, yet there is no doubt,<note place="margin">In locum.</note> but as <hi>Paraeus</hi> rightly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the admonition here giuen extends to our auoidance of all other foule errors about the doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines of faith. For if wee bee vntoucht of this falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, there are beſides this, many others, iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20577:21"/>to God and dangerous to ſoules, wherewith if wee are likely to be tainted, our Apoſtles watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word is ſtill in force. <hi>Erre not my beloued brethren.</hi> Let me then (taking my text in its iuſt latitude) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into that, wherevnto I haue deſtinated my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, for this place and time; which is to lay downe a courſe how wee may recouer others and preſerue our ſelues form errors in religion, that ſo this monitory ſpeech of out Apoſtle may take ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect among vs. And of this, as God, the hower, and your patience will permit.</p>
            <p>Concerning our recouery of others faln into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, though herein much may bee ſaid, yet in this ſcantneſſe of time, it will be thriftieſt for me, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue only our Apoſtles method herein, <hi>first</hi> wee muſt haue a care as well to inſtruct them, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them, ſo doth Saint <hi>Iames;</hi> who together with his cry <hi>Nolite errare,</hi> vſeth very powerfull ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, drawne from the nature of God, and the true cauſes of ſinne; whereby hee proues that God cannot be a tempter to euill, as reading the chapter you ſhall perceiue. And indeed it cannot be but a fruitleſſe imperiouſneſſe to command a man not to erre &amp; not teach him with all the folly of his error, &amp; what reaſons there are to withſtand it; and here I cannot but diſlike the courſe taken vp by ſome of our calling, who ſometimes in the pulpet doe with greater eagernes of paſſion, inveigh againſt popiſh errors, then ſoundneſſe of iudgement, and choice of arguments refute them; this rather advantageth then reformeth falſhood; putting this frump into
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20577:22"/>our aduerſaries mouths; wee ſee a will rather then a power in our oppoſits to convince vs of error, for we heare much noiſe, little reaſon; and who are they that we ſhould credit them, vpon their bare words, and weake aſſertion only: but this is a fault moſt ſeene in the country, and therefore not to bee inſiſted on in this place.</p>
            <p>A ſecond direction is afforded from the curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous language of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> in our text; the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he confutes, comes not ſhort of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, yet the Apoſtle abſtaines from that harſher terme, and molifies that had opinion into the gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler name of <hi>error</hi> and now hee calls from this error he ſalutes his ſchollers after a milde &amp; louing man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Erre not beloued brethren.</hi> If we could doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good vpon others errors, this behauiour is of all others the moſt winning; to come to the handling of our brethrens ſores, with brotherly minds, full of loue and compaſſion. <hi>Aſeruant of the Lords,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially he that doth the Lords ſervice in freeing mens ſoules from error,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.24.25</note> Muſt be as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> deſcribes him, <hi>gentle to all men, apt to teach, patient, in meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelues, if God peraduenture will giue them repentance, to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging of the truth;</hi> and ſurely great reaſon we haue to ſhew humanity to humane errors; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring how difficult a matter it is for poore ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant men, ſo euery way beſet with the ſnares of error, to eſcape all danger, yea not forgetting that wee our ſelues are but men, and may poſſibly haue as great ſtaines, in our iudgement, as thoſe wee
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20577:22"/>would expunge in others; how ſoeuer, by dealing with our brethren after a faire, &amp; mild demenaour, wee ſhall render them more docile, and tractable, it being the nature of many to lend a more patient eare to thoſe of whom they haue an opinion that they proceed in loue: the mind delights rather to follow then to be lead, and rather to be lead, then drawne, violence making it the more contumati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: it fares with him that hath put on error, as it did with him in the <hi>Apoloag</hi> whom the ſunne faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſerenely ſhining vpon, might haue woode to caſt off his cloake, which the bluſtering winde made him to keepe cloſer on; and ſurely there are ſome that if gently admoniſhed will both reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence their inſtructer, and embrace his advice, but if ouer roughly and ſmartingly handled,<note place="margin">Salvian,</note> will rather be exaſperated then reformed <hi>facti ſunt ingeſta a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crius veritate peiores; they are made worſe by a truth too too eagerly put vpon them.</hi> They ſeeme then ſmally acquainted with the diſcretion of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhers, or condition of humane nature, who fly into the face of their erring brethren, with biting inuectiues, and rigorous puniſhments, as if it were all one to raile and convince, condemne and teach, or as if it were a brauer thing for Chriſtians to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy power then loue, in the correcting of their brethren; I ſpeake not againſt the due puniſhment of men obſtinate and irreclaimable, but that they may not bee ſo, I would haue all louing meanes firſt tryed to recall them; yea and when a ſevere ſtroke is giuen I would haue it inflicted with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20577:23"/>of vnfained ſorrow and loue, as the <hi>primitiue</hi> Church did her cenſures with <hi>much mourning;</hi> as may bee gatherered by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paules</hi> epiſtles with whom to <hi>correct</hi> &amp; <hi>lament</hi> are ſymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimas as the iuditious writer of the <hi>Trent</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells hiſtory hath noted,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.2. 2 Cot. 2.4. <hi>Hiſtor, Confil. Trident.</hi>
               </note> who obſerues farther, that in thoſe times <hi>the exceſſe of charity in correcting did make the corrector feele greater paine then the corrected;</hi> the proceedings of latter times, haue bin ſo harſh and feirce, that it may bee thought that ſome haue beene ſo far from greiving at the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of others, that rather they haue beene glad of them, eſpecially if they bee ſuch, the ſedulous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery &amp; puniſhment whereof would as they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped inſinuate them into the fauours of the great ones, of the world, men thus being more beholding to the errors of others, then their owne vertues for their preferments, or if this humour hath not tooke them, it is to be feared another hath, full of malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant vaineglory; while they ſomewhat reioiceat the daily outburſting of error, that ſo they might haue worke, if not for their authority to vſe the rod, yet for their learning to imploy the pen or tongue in confuting them. I thinke it a worthy worke to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince erronious doctrines, and I hope this place will neuer want thoſe, that ſhall performe it readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſolidly, but to deſire errors to make oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this skill, is a perverſeambition, voide of all brotherly charity,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>132.</hi> ad Florenlinam.</note> 
               <hi>non vt quod ſcimus doceamus aliorum ignor antiam opt are debemus</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſten, to the end we may teach the world what wee know,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20577:23"/>wee may not wiſh for the ignorance or error of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> But ſo much ſhall ſuffice for the courſe inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated in our Apoſtles proceeding, fit for vs to take in the recouering of others from their errors; how wee ſhall preſerue our ſelues, it remaines to the preſcribed.</p>
            <p>Error is a ſickneſſe of the ſoule: and the chiefe part, at leaſt the firſt degree of the cure, is to know and ſtop the fountaine of the diſeaſe. The cauſes of error are many; I will not touch vpon thoſe which may craue the mercy of our excuſe and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and which are now ſo incident to our nature, that they are paſt our avoidance; for it is miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chife ſufficiently knowne and felt, that our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent his inordinat and ambitious deſire of ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wide knowledge, brought himſelfe, and his vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py poſterity into the darke priſon of ignorance; where lying, and <hi>God</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſets it forth,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 14.2.</note> 
               <hi>looking downe from heauen vpon the children of men, to ſee if there were any that would vnderſtand, he findes not one they are all corrupt</hi> as in their <hi>wills</hi> ſo in their <hi>vnderſtandings:</hi> hee that readeth the third to the <hi>Romans</hi> where this paſſage of Dauid is alleaged ſhall perceaue,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.9.11.</note> that no fauourable <hi>ſynecdoche</hi> can ſaue any of the poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> from his <hi>epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demicall</hi> contagion: And although God the great Phyſition of ſoules, by his ſpirit, by his begotten word the ſonne, and by that word which he put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mouthes of his prophets, and Apoſtles, hath purged the minds of many of much ignorance, and made their vnderſtanding more cleare and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20577:24"/>yet whether it bee that the diſeaſe, is too deepely rooted in our nature to bee driuen out vpon a ſodaine, or whether it bee that God will haue ſOme reliques thereof abide in vs, to containe vs within the bounds of humility, and doth not thinke it fit we ſhould inioy all our happineſſe at once: whatſoeuer the reaſon is, euen the beſt men doe ofter finde in themſelues certaine grudgings of this malady. Not only they bewray their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance but their error, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ingeniouſly confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>that before he went into the ſanctuary, the ſchoole of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.17.22.</note> in a matter of no ſmall importance, <hi>he was fooliſh and ignorant, and euen brutiſh before God.</hi> The truth is (for an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath taught it) that in this life,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.9.</note> 
               <hi>we know but in part,</hi> and no wonder is it, if this penurious and incompleat knowledge leaue vs in the hands of diuers errors. But this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſeebleneſſe of the vnderſtanding (although queſtionleſſe it be the parent of ſundry miſtakes, I come to pitty not to laſh; eſpecially where there is a care to heale and ſtrengthen ſuch weakneſſe of the minde, by thoſe wholſome remedies which God hath preſcribed; and there be no willing fomenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, but all manly reſitance againſt erroneous fancies; and if alſo ſince wee want the happineſſe of being free from error and ignorance, wee want not the wiſdome to bee forry for our defects, andto pray for their forgiueneſſe and couering in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The leaders into errors againſt which my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is ſpecially bent, come forth not ſo much
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20577:24"/>from the coaſts of a naturally weake vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as of ſome morally bad affections, which muſt be ſubdued or error will bee victorious. For that the affections are of great force, to ſway the iudgement, wee need not marvaile, ſince the will is the moſt imperious faculty of the ſoule, &amp; makes vſe of the vnderſtanding but as a councellor; now as when a prince is ſtrongly let vpon a thing, and is reſolued to haue his owne way, the councellors many times what for feare, what for loue; or very flattery are plyant inough to his purpoſe, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſuffer themſelues, to be corrupted, that they may appeare ſerviceable; ſo when once the will is in ordinately affected and mainely bent to that ill vpon which the affection is placed, it giues little leaſure and no leaue to the vnderſtanding to diſſent from it, yea it dimns the eye of the ſould, that it cannot diſcerne the truth, or faſhions the ſight to its owne wrong guiſe,<note place="margin">Iud. 16.16.19.20.</note> when I read the ſtory of <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> I meet with no vnfit <hi>Embleme</hi> of this the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections dealing with the vnderſtanding; <hi>Dalilah</hi> firſt allures the man to betray his owne ſtrength and then puts him into the hands of his enimies; ſo doe the affections firſt emaſculat the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and corrupt its abilities, and then deliuer it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer into the hands of ſome dangerous falſhood. To the making good this point I ſupoſe euery mans experience will afford euidence. For who cannot witneſſe ſo much, that when his minde hath beene tranſported with the violence of ſome bad paſſion, or deſire, hee hath conceiued ſo and ſo of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20577:25"/>things and hath beene ſomewhat eager in the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his conceit, who afterward, when this ſtorme of paſſion is gone ouer, and the ſoule hath recouered her wonted tranquility and cleereneſſe; obſerues his miſtake, changeth his opinion, and growes ſomewhat aſhamed of his vnderſtanding. Now if the ſuddaine vntuly commotions and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton deſires of the minde vitiat and rauiſh the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and beget diuers errors, how ſhould not ſuch be peſtered with theſe miſhapen bratts, in whom vnbridled ſinfull affections keepe a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing court, and whoſe whole life is an habituated vitiouſneſſe: Nor is it nothing to our purpoſe, that wee may obſerue thoſe grand maſters of error, the hereticks in all ages, for the moſt part haue beene ill mannered men, &amp; ſuch in whom the diſtempers either of the concupiſcible or iraſcible part, of the ſoule, haue beene eminent. St <hi>Paule</hi> prophecying of the <hi>laſt perilo us times</hi> ſhewes <hi>that men ſhall bee ſelfe amorous,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.1.2.3.4.5.6.8.13.</note> couetous, boaſters, what not,</hi> &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes declares that of this rotten timber ſhould teachers of <hi>falſhood be made deceiuing, &amp; being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, reſisting the truth, as Iannes and Iambres did Moſes:</hi> nor can I thinke that alwaies the hereſies of theſe men did produce their vitiouſneſſe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that the vitiouſneſſe of theſe men did thruſt them vpon their hereſies. They were <hi>firſt men of corrupt mindes</hi> and then <hi>reprobate concerning the faith,</hi> as the Apoſtle orders his deſcription: and ſurely if wee take a liſt, of the preſent errors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which wee moſt condemne, it
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20577:25"/>were no hard matter to finde out their genealogy and ſhew that the greateſt part of their falſe doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, and bad practiſes, come as it were out of the loines of couetouſneſſe, or ambition, or licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. If then we would not fall backe into the ſame, or plunge our ſelues into as bad errors, wee muſt take heed of certaine vitious humors &amp; affections, the accuſtomed originalls of falſe opinions in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of religion, the chiefe whereof I ſhall name vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</p>
            <p>And firſt omitting to charge that natuall flatnes and dulneſſe of ſpirit in ſome (which I had rather commiſerat) there is a voluntary ſluggiſhneſſe and affected lazineſſe of the minde, which cannot but expoſe a man to error; for ſince error eaſily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes an ignorance of the truth, and ſince truth doth commonly keepe ſo much ſtate, as not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale her ſelfe to any but thoſe who ſtudiouſly ſeeke her; this ſlouthfull, and negligent fort of men muſt needs miſſe her, and fall into error, ſince they will not take the paines of diligent inquiry into things; there is naturally in all of vs a cloudines and foggy darkneſſe of ignorance, and nothing will ſo much thicken it, in our breaſts, as this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Iſdor Peluſiot ep. lib. <hi>3.</hi> epiſt. <hi>191.</hi>
               </note> this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritleſſe, and languiſhing ſloth of the minde: if the ſoule be of neuer ſo rich mettall, idleneſſe will fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new and ruſt it, and make it vnſeruiceable, in the warre we haue againſt error. Obſerue the inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of theſe men, and ſee if they bee not worthy to be miſtaken; out of a loue they haue to eaſe their owne vnderſtanding, and to giue the powers, both
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20577:26"/>of body and ſoule ſome reſt; in the queſtions o religion, they accept them with ready faith, as they are ſtated by others, reputed learned, or as they are vulgarly held;<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.21. 1 Ioh. 4.1.</note> as for that aduice of the <hi>Apoſtle S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule, proue all things, and hold that which is good,</hi> or that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn, try the ſpirits whether they are of God,</hi> it is with them too cumberſome, and tedious a buſineſſe; but while they giue this prone aſſent to aſſertions, and will not take the paines to examine them; while they thus haue made an abſolute reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of their iudgements, to the braines and faith of others, and thinke it reaſon inough to beleeue, their elders in time, or betters in place, though they ſpeake without reaſon; Lord whether will theſe be carried; into what pitte of error may they not quickly fall! Since it may be their lucke, not to meet, with the beſt leaders, and the leaders of theſe beare their faith along with them. To this miſchiefe men are not alwaies ſubiect, whoſe capacities are not great, or whoſe vnderſtanding is yet in its minori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but euen free and able men put themſelues into the hazard,<note place="margin">Minutius in Octavio.</note> to liue the more eaſily and idly, <hi>taedio inveſtigandae penitus veritatis, cuilibet opinioni temerè potiùs ſuccumbere malunt, quàm in explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando pertinaci diligentiâ perſeuerare,</hi> as hee ſaid not amiſſe in the dialogue of <hi>Minutius Faelix. out of a wearineſſe to ſearch deepely into truth, they had rather raſhly I may ſay baſely fall into the hands of any opinion, then perſeueringly indure the paines, of a thorough enguiry.</hi> But I diſmiſſe theſe.</p>
            <p>The next ſort of men moſt obnoxious to error,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20577:26"/>are of a more elate and lofty ſpirit,<note place="margin">Act. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Simon Mangus</hi> conſorts, that would haue himſelfe thought to bee <hi>ſome great one,</hi> as it is in the acts, and all antiquity proclaimes his pride, a malady diſcouered by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paule, in the ſixt chapter of his first epistle to Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.4. 2 Pet. 2.10.</note> and by Saint Peter in his ſecond epiſtle and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond chapter thereof,</hi> in the faſe teachers, and <hi>ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſeducers</hi> of their time, and we may not wonder if the man that is poſſeſſed with the ſpirit of pride be carried into errors, if wee ſhall obſerue his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and garbe a little. For firſt, whereas there is nothing that doth caſt a ſooner, or thicker miſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the vnderſtanding, then an opinionate dotage vpon our ſelues, this arrogant man ſetts too high a price vpon himſelfe, and his owne abilities; and whether his pride be conioined with ignorance or learning (as 'tis hard to ſay which is the more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky coniunction) he is confident he erres not, and ſo indeed drawes neerer to error, the winde of pride hurting his eyeſight, this man caſts a ſcorne vpon what ſo euer elder times, or riper iudgements can ſhes him, contrary to that which he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited. <hi>Nectorius</hi> boaſted <hi>Saram ſcripturam ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vincent. Lyrin. cap. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſolum intelligere, he firſt and alone vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood the ſcriptures,</hi> and all other <hi>Doctors</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him meere <hi>Ignaroes;</hi> hee deſerued to erre, that would be wiſe alone. Thus a proud man, as if all the light were in himſelfe, diſdaines the ſoclety of other mens iudgements: of which branne are thoſe of our times with whom (ſaucily herein leuelling God with themſelues) 1000 <hi>yeares are but as</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 90.4.</note>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:20577:27"/>
               <hi>yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> no regard had by them to Godly anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and the conſtant iudgement of the Church in the beſt ages thereof: and what may wee thinke of their ſpirit, by whom the moſt renowned di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines of our preſent times, to whom the happy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of our Church next vnder God is ſo much indebted àre ſleightned and caſt off as <hi>tribo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary</hi> writers. I doe not ſay but that there are ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes of iudgement in the auntient, and errors may be found in our moderne worthies; and I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it a ſeruility vnworthy of free and generous Chriſtians, to mancipat our vnderſtandings to the iudgement of others, which may carry vs into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors as ſoone as any other thing, as I haue already noted: I onely call for ſo much modeſty, and good maners, that when wee perceaue a doctrine to bee generally receaued, by holy and learned men, in our owne and elder Churches, we take them along with vs in our inquiry after truth, and not haſtily breake from them, to follow our wone way vpon a preſumptuous conceit of our wone iudgements which we haue as much if not more reaſon to miſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſt, as wee haue to miſdoubt other mens. Againe whereas naturall reaſon is but a blind &amp; wandring guide in matters ſpirituall, this man is too ftifly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the dictats thereof, it is a foule ſtaine of iudgement when a man conceiues that there are the ſame bounds of things naturall, &amp; of his owne apprehenſion (for things may bee in themſelues, though they be not vnderſtood by vs) and it is an vneuen meaſuring, of a mans ſeſe when hee ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20577:27"/>there is ſame latitude of his owne, and humane vnderſtanding, as if hee knew as much as another can know; but ſolly is then enraged euen to balſphemy, when in an ouer proud indulgence to his owne wit, a man ſhall thinke that God were able to ſpeake or doe nothing which he is not able to comprehend: of this giantlike preſumption, was <hi>Eunomius</hi> of whom <hi>Theodoret</hi> reports that hee gaue out, <hi>he had the ſame notice of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Haeret. fabul. comp. cap. de Eunomio.</note> 
               <hi>as God had of himſelfe</hi> as no odds were to bee put betwixt a finite, and infinite knowledge: for as <hi>Lactantius</hi> wiſely ſaith: <hi>Nibilinter deum hominem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diſtaret, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſilia illa maie ſtatis aeternae cogitatio aſſequeret ur humana, there were no diſtance betwixt God &amp; man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lact. lib. 1. c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>if humane cogitation could attaine vnto the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes of the aeternall maiesty.</hi> And indeed while we extoll the ſoueraignty of our reaſon, we vnawares debaſe the dignity of that thing whereof reaſon is the teacher. For it can be no great matter which ſo narrow and ſhallow a thing, as humane vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding leſt to hyis owne forces, can helpe vs to the knowledge of: nay it may ſooner bee an error then a trifle. Adde hereunto that whereas an ill carriage of our ſelues towards the ſcriptures, (the rule of truth) is the readiſet downefall into error: the proud perſon either vainely ſuppoſeth it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee Gods word which exceeds his wone witt; of ſaucily murmures that God ſhould challenge our aſſent, and giue vs not alwaies logicall demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trations of what he faith (as if it were not inough for this ſupreame legiſlator to pronounce a truth
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20577:28"/>or law vnleſſe he argue it before the tribunall of our reaſon) or elſe he giues a faaint credit to what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer croſſeth his affection, or if he muſt needs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret, he hath a will rather to wreſt the ſcriptures to his opinion, then bend his opinion to the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to impoſe his ſence vpon the word, then ſetch his ſence from the word, as if he meant to lead, and not to follow the holy ghoſt; and theſe interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are for the moſt part made in haſt, for hee takes it to bee a kinde of diſparagement, to the nimbleneſſe of his witt to ſeeme to doubt, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberat long, and whiles hee makes more care to haſten then examine his opinion, he ſpeedily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth and as eaſily errs. for want of mature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation; there is one euill of pride more; (making way to error) not to be omitted, it is a ſtudiouſneſſe of nouelty; I know not how the witt of man hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by pride, diſdaines as a wretched thing, and a matter of no glory to tread in the ſteps of others, that haue gone before, and thus while wee are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to ſay what others haue not hit vpon, the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination hunting and ranging about; ſome pretty and perhaps probable ſtrange opinion is ſtarted vp before it, which it runns away with in very quick ſent and great delight, we are marveilouſly favora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our owne conceits, and although at firſt wee giue not any ſtrong beleife vnto them, yet wee lend them many harty wiſhes that they were true; and with long well wiſhing, in time they come within the conſines of ſome ſetled allowance, and at laſt paſſe into our vnmoueable aſſent; and now
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20577:28"/>when all is done, the thing will be found to bee of more fineneſſe then ſtrength, of more ſubtilty then truth: theſe are the perills of pride, if it bee ioined with learning, but if the proud ſpirited man is not conſcious of much learnning, yet if hee findes ſome falſhes of goodneſſe, in himſelfe, hee thinks that want abundantly ſupplyed by certaine revelations of the ſpirit, whoſe great acquaintance he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe to be, that now he thinkes that he hath arriued to an impeccancy of iudgement in matters ſpirituall: and (as <hi>Vincentius</hi> ſpeakes of ſome,<note place="margin">Cap. 37.</note> that boaſted of the grace of the ſpirit <hi>indiuiduated to them</hi>) <hi>that hee is ordered by God, that carried as it were by Angells hands, he can neuer daſh his foot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any stone of error:</hi> but alas this is the proneſt way to the wildeſt error, when euery outleaping &amp; wantoneſſe of fancy (as it happeneth among fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticall enthuſiaſts) ſhall be reputed an inſpiration and reuelation of the ſpirit: nor doth pride by ſo many waies lead into error, but which is worſt, leaues the minde as a finall pray to it: for it makes the vnderſtanding fierce and vntractable: every contradiction, euery affront from truth is reputed a contumely, the miſhapen iſſue of the minde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing borne muſt now bee kept; all retractations are baſeneſſe, and diſhonour; thus, that men may not ſeeme to be men, and to haue erred they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come hereticks: ſo contumatious a murſe of error is pride.</p>
            <p>To pride in the thired place let vs adioine as of neereſt familiarity with it, the angry ſpirit of facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20577:29"/>and contention,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.8. Iam. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>to be contentious and not to bee obedient to truth,</hi> are things coupled together by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iames</hi> hath rightly obſerued as <hi>of enuy ſo of ſtrife, where it is there is</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>an vnſetled and tumultuous confuſion, and euery euill worke,</hi> the obſeruation hath place, if wee apply it to the ſtate of the ſoule, there cannot be but much confuſion, and entercourſe of error, where conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath got in. Doe but obſerue the men who know not how to hold any thing without paſſion, how oft they ſhame reaſon, to gratify their pettiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: if a queſtion bee moued, which moues their choller with little or no choice they will croſſe whatſoeuer you propoſe, their humor carrying them not ſo much to know as oppugne truth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which if they can bee witty, it is a braue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency; &amp; when once in the rage of pride and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, their error is marcht forth, it is a difficult mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to worke a retrait, and though you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unice them, they will not bee perſwaded; their fury will proceed in the brable, vntill they haue impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their brable into a hereſy, this pettiſhneſſe when it is ſowred into malice, hath often carried ſome (who would bee at the moſt diametral diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, with their aduerſaries) not only to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from their perſons, but their doctrines, even when they haue beene moſt ſound and orthodox. And here let me giue warning, that in matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, wee vſe no inordinate haſt in binding our iudgements to the opinions of others, whom either the fame of learning, or the greatneſſe of place, or
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20577:29"/>the neereneſſe of blood, or the likeneſſe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners or the ſweetneſſe of profit (all which haue great forces vpon the mind) hath wrought into our eſtimation; for this caſts vs into faction, wherein if a man be once imbarked, he will runne a hazard of erring, becauſe he hath left the guidance of reaſon, and is lead only by certaine preiudices, and antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations borrowed from the perſons of men, which ſtrongly ſway which ſide ſoeuer bee taken. Laſtly I muſt report, as an occaſioner of ſome errors a too violent oppoſition of ſome errors: for ſince it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denyed but that there are dangers on either hand of truth, and ſince it muſt be confeſſed, that truth hath not the good hap alwaies to meet with well aduiſed champions, it may poſſibly fall out, and vſually doth, that while thy oppoſe ſome falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods with an extreame, and vnlimited deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, while they take that to bee beſt in religion, which is at furtheſt diſtance from the error they come to oppugne, &amp; while they are ouer impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly carried to the ſlaughter of their adverſaries opinions; in the ſervor of contentious zeale they fling themſelues into points euery way as crroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as thoſe which they haue incountred; and ſo haue not left but changed a falſhood, and it may be to the worſe, and haue beene found <hi>liers againſt God,</hi> at leaſt <hi>for him</hi> which <hi>Iob</hi> blames.<note place="margin">Iob. 13.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I haue done with the angrier part of the ſoule; ſhe hath her luſtfulneſſe alſo, as great an enimy to truth: let me then in the fourth place, indite coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, &amp; ambition, who peruerting the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20577:30"/>muſt needs induce error; how many falſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions did couetouſneſſe helpe the lying Prophets too of old?<note place="margin">Eſay 56.11.</note> The preiſts in <hi>Eſaies</hi> time <hi>were become ſhepheards that could not vnder ſtand for they were as greedy as their doggs, they looked to their owne way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim 6. Tatus 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>euery one for his owne againe from his quarter.</hi> Who were they in the Apoſtles time, <hi>which cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, betrayed, forſooke the faith, but men who ſuppoſed gaine to be Godlineſſe, and who were ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with filthy lucre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.14.15.</note> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> giues vs their cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, thoſe as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, who had hearts <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed with couetous practiſes, right Balaamites; were the men who forſooke the right path and went actray,<note place="margin">Ifid. de ſcripe. eccli.</note> louing the wages of vnrighteouſneſſe.</hi> Euen that famous <hi>Oſius</hi> of <hi>Corduba</hi> if <hi>Iſidore</hi> charge him iuſtly, conſented to the <hi>Arrian</hi> impiety, <hi>that in his olde age he might not looſe thoſe riches which he had got together in his youth;</hi> and certainely the feare of loſing, the hope of gaining theſe tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things hath ſo prevailed with many, that wee muſt conclude with holy <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>the loue of money is the root of all euill, which while ſome coueted after, they haue erred from the faith, and peirced them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues</hi> (I am ſure the <hi>Church</hi> of God) <hi>through with diuers ſorrowes.</hi> And indeed I ſee not how truth can be thought vpon in the duſt, and noiſe, of worldly imployments, or grow vp amidſt the choaking thornes of worldly cares: how can the breaſts of men be wells of the pure and liuing wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of truth,<note place="margin">Gen. 26.15.</note> when couetous luſts, as ſo many <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listins</hi> haue <hi>ſtopt them vp and filled them with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20577:30"/>earth.</hi> A worldling already hath admitted, that grand error into his heart, that <hi>riches is the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne good,</hi> fom which <hi>idolatry,</hi> a man may quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlip into any hereſy that will ſort with it,<note place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> ſuch a much worme conſiders not what is true, but what is profitable: nay ſuch a man feares ſome truth as much as a theife, leaſt it come forth to take his purſe, and leſſen his heap. The like accuſation is to bee framed againſt <hi>Ambition,</hi> for let a man inordinatly affect worldy grace or preferment, if hee cannot thriue in the way of truth, his diſcontented and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengefull heart, will turne ouer vnto ſuch opinions, which may bee profeſſed with better preferment. Beſides the men that ſtudy preferment, are of a very ſupple and plyant vnderſtanding, and can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue at the pleaſure of another, at the diſpoſition of him, who diſpoſeth of the dignities hee expects; as if he had loſt his owne ſoule and were wholy actuated with the ſoule of his <hi>Maecenas,</hi> In the meane while <hi>how can ye beleeue as</hi> our ſauiour told the Iewes <hi>which receaue honour one of another and ſeeke not the honour which cometh from God alone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.44.</note> how can a man alwaies thinke aright that muſt thinke as the <hi>grandees,</hi> who oft are as great in crime as place, will haue him. The Apoſtle hath a text, perhaps miſread, doubtleſſe miſvnderſtood by the <hi>Eceboliuſes</hi> of our age who are too oft found <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> when it ſhould bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſeruing not the Lord but the time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. <hi>12.11.</hi> vide ſtephani lecti. varias.</note> and that in the moſt reprobate ſence of the phraſe; for they obſerue not the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (as the Apoſtle might meane) wherein they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20577:31"/>might beſt doe good, but whereby they might bee moſt great, by applying themſelues to the humors of thoſe, who if ſoothed, are likelieſt to preferre. Ere I altogether diſmiſſe this point, let me touch an euill, neere of kinne to ambition &amp; as dangerous to truth:<note place="margin">Gal. 6.12. Acts. 15.1.</note> Certaine popular men there are, ſuch as thoſe <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> in the dayes of the truth, who would haue <hi>blinded</hi> the religion of <hi>Christ</hi> with the <hi>ordinances</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>ſuperadded circumciſion to baptiſme</hi> perhaps that both Iew and Gentile might be pleaſed; ſuch as theſe I ſay there are, who to gaine good eſtimation with different ſects, giue faire quarter to all opinions; and theſe commonly talke of reconciling religions, and compoſing of controverſies, that all may goe away contented. I know it is a commendable indeuour of Godly men, to ſeeke the vnion of Chriſtian churches; and let them be deteſted, who by needleſſe ſtrifes &amp; exaſperations, make the rents of the Church wider: thoſe I here intend, who loue their owne fame, more then peace, and peace more then truth: which they care not how they pare to the quicke, that they may gaine the applauſe of moderate and well tempered men.</p>
            <p>In the fift and laſt place we are to brand a licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and diſſolute life,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.19.</note> with the ſtile of <hi>corruptor of the faith, ſome putting away a good conſcience</hi> (which inferrs the leading a bad life) <hi>concerning the faith, haue made ſhipwracke</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> repors of the <hi>bringers in of damnable haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies that they had their pernitious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1.2.10.14.19.</note> or as ſome
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20577:31"/>bookes <hi>laſciuious waies, that they walked after the fleſh in the lusts of vncleaneſſe; that they had eyes full of adultery and that could not ceaſe from ſinne, great promiſers of liberty to others they themſelues being the ſervants of corruption, as the Apoſtle</hi> largely deſcribes their manners: Now ſuch as theſe hauing hearts already full of ſenſuality, there is no roome for heauenly contemplations of chaſt truth; whatſoeuer vigor, and cleereneſſe and intentiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the mind, is requiſite to the right diſcerning of things, the very ſtrength of the ſoule, is loſt in the armes of <hi>Dalilah;</hi> frugality &amp; ſobriety (the ſinewes of a ſound iudgement) are looſed; beſides there are not any of thoſe holy and ſeuere truths in Gods word but theſe men wiſh and long they were falſe, and a little matter will improue a wiſh into a beleefe, <hi>quod volumus facile credimus;</hi> as on the contrary he is apt to take thoſe doctrines to be true which are indulgent to his dareling vices; he would faine ſinne with ſome warrant, that hee may pacify fame abroad, and conſcience at home if it were poſſible; <hi>natur a hominis procliuis in vitia vult non modo cum veniâ ſed cum ratione peccare,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> c.</note> ſaith Lact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antius</hi> and therefore he ſedulouſly hunts after and would gladly finde out ſome doctrines vnder whoſe protection he may offend, in this purfuite euen the paſſages of ſcriptures are ſerched into by ſome, to ſee what patronage they will afford to their intemperances, that ſo they may ſecurely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the pleaſure of ill deeds; making that their poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which is appointed to be their medicine.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:20577:32"/>
            <p> Thus haue I (Fathers and brethren) as breifely as ſo many particulars would permit, ſhewed that they are our morrall evills to which wee may lay moſt of our errors in matters of religion; that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſhould now enlarge my ſelfe, but cannot (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I ſhould treſpaſſe to much vpon your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) is, that for the avoidance of error wee would all of vs ſtudy true piety, which ſtanding in the <hi>feare of God,</hi> muſt needs be the <hi>beginning of ſauing wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> this feare it being grounded in loue, will make you ſtill haue an eye to your fathers will: and <hi>if a man will doe the will of my Father</hi> ſaith his ſon <hi>he ſhall know of the doctrine whether it bee of God:</hi> now the will of God is, that you bee induſtrious, humble, peaceable, moderate in your deſires, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in your liues, and euery way contrary to the misbehauiored men which I haue ſet before you: bee thus and the victory againſt error may ſooneſt be atchiued; ſooner a great deale, then by all the proviſions of naturall witt, or ſecular learning. One of the heathens had this ſpeech,<note place="margin">Aug. ep. <hi>20.</hi> Socrates.</note> 
               <hi>Quibus ſatis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſum vt nihil mallent eſſe quam viros bonos his reliqua facilis eſt doctrina:</hi> ſo may I ſay diuine knowledge will eaſily impart it ſelfe to ſuch, who can be perſwaded to deſire to be nothing ſo much as true hearted Chriſtians, and can be content to be guided by Gods ſpirit, for ſuch <hi>haue the vnction</hi> whereof S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhall know all things,</hi> all things meet for ſuch knowledge, and ſeruice of God here, as ſhall make them partakers of his ſight and glory hereafter. David giues euery good man
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20577:32"/>great aſſurance when he asketh, <hi>what man is hee that feareth the Lord, and ſubioynes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 25.12.</note> 
               <hi>him ſhall hee teach the way that he ſhall chooſe,</hi> &amp; who is lead by God is out of the road of deſtroying error. O lord, by thy word and ſpirit guide vs all here preſent, by thy ſonne, who is the truth, bring vs to thy ſonne who is the life; and that it may pleaſe thee to <hi>bring into the way of truth all others that haue erred &amp; are deceiued we beſeech thee to heare vs good Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Letany.</note> to whom all praiſe and glory bee aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed now and euer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
